<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration or remonstrance, to His Majesties loyal and faithful subjects; touching brokers, usurers, scrivenors, and solicitors: for, and in behalf of all merchants, citizens, countrey-men, and other His Majesties good subjects, within the kingdoms of England, Scotland, Ireland, and Dominion of Wales.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1043_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207943</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866958</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866958</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119247</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82249)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119247)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 154:E1043[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration or remonstrance, to His Majesties loyal and faithful subjects; touching brokers, usurers, scrivenors, and solicitors: for, and in behalf of all merchants, citizens, countrey-men, and other His Majesties good subjects, within the kingdoms of England, Scotland, Ireland, and Dominion of Wales.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for George Horton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept 4".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Usury --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119247:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OR Remonſtrance, TO HIS MAJESTIES Loyal and Faithful Subjects; TOUCHING
<list>
                  <item>Brokers,</item>
                  <item>Uſurers,</item>
                  <item>Scrivenors,</item>
                  <item>And Solicitors:</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For, and in behalf of all Merchants, Citizens, Countrey-men, and other His Majeſties good Subjects, within the Kingdoms of England, Scotland, Ireland, and Dominion of Wales.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>George-Horton,</hi> 1660. <add>Sept 4</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119247:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119247:2"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION TO All His Majeſties loving Subjects, touching Brokers Uſurers, Scrivenors, and Solicitors; For, and in behalf of all Shoo-makers, Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Butchers, Victuallers, Chandlers, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Clothworkers, Taylors, Wire-drawers, Gold Smiths, and Silver-Smiths.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the reſt of His Sacred Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties many Illuſtrious Titles, which like fair and beautiful Flowers, do adorn &amp; bedeck His Royal Crown, there's <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one exc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eds and excels all the reſt, aſwell in Vertue as in Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119247:3"/>and that is His Title of Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. And, indeed, as that Title is his Majeſties Honour, ſo the Truth of it is His Subjects Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For, neith<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the higheſt Prov<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c tions, nor the ſtrongeſt Tempt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions that ever Prince met withall, hath been able to ſlake his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ictorious Faith, nor abate his holy Zeal: Witneſſe his Gracious Majeſties firſt Act, after his Return <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Exerciſe of his Regal Power, in his early and timely ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Prophaneneſſe and diſcountenancing debaucht perſons, who know not how to expreſſe their Thankfulneſſe unto GOD for Mercies, but by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful drinking them away; a practiſe his Majeſties Soul a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hors.</p>
            <p>Theſe his eminent Vertues, and excellent Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations that God hath beſtowed upon Him, to make him every way wo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thy and fit for Government, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the Parliament, with joyful <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earts, to make their humble Addreſſes to his Majeſty for his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Aſſent to ſeveral Bills; Amongſt whi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, the Bill intituled, An Act to prevent the taking of exceſſive Uſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, was by his Maj<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſty ſigned, to the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of all Loyal and Faithful Subjects.</p>
            <p>The reſtraining men of avaritious minds whoſe Conſciences are as large as their Bags, will be a great eaſe to the People, and an inablement to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119247:3"/>the Merchants the better to go on with their Trades. They are the laborious Bees that bring in Honey into his Majeſties Hive; and Uſurers are the lazie, idle Dron<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat rob this precious Hive of the honey.</p>
            <p>For preventing all ſuch Abuſes for the Future, It is Enacted by the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, and the Lords and Commons in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Aſſembled, That no per<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on or perſons whatſoever, from and after the 29th day of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1660. upon any Contract, ſhall from and after the ſaid Day, take directly o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> indi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ectly for Loane of any Mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, Wares, Merchandiſe, or o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities whatſoever, above the value o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſix pounds for the Forbearance of one hundred pounds for a year, and ſo after that Rate for a greater or leſſer ſum or for a longer or ſhorter time. And that all Bonds, Contracts, and Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'s whatſoever, made after the time afore<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid, for payment of any Principall or Money to be lent or covenan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to be perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med upon or for any Uſury.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119247:4"/>
            <p> Whereupon or whereby there ſhall be reſerved or taken above the rate of ſix pounds in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred as aforeſa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſhall be utterly void.</p>
            <p>And all perſons what<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oever, who ſhall after the 29 day of September, are hereby deſired to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, That if any perſon or perſons ſhall take, accept, and receive, by way or means of any corrupt Bargain, Loan, Exchange, Shift, or Intereſt of any Wares or Merchandiſe whatſoever, or by any deceitful way, or conveyance, for the forbearing or giving day of payment for one whole year, of and for their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or other thing, above the ſum of ſix pounds for the forbearing of one hundred pounds for a year, and ſo after that Rate for a greater or leſſer ſum, or for a longer and ſhorter Terme, ſhall forfeit &amp; loſe for every ſuch Offence, the treble value of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Wares, Merchandiſe, and other things ſo lent, bargained, ſold, exchanged, or ſhifted. And all Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venors, Brokers, Solicitors, Drivers of Bargains for Contra<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts, who ſhall after the ſaid 39. day of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, take or receive, directly or indirectly, any Sum or Sums of Money, or other Reward or Thing for Brokage, Soliciting, Driving, or procuring the Loan, or forbearing of any Sum or Sums of Money, over and above the Rate or value of five ſhillings for the Loane, or forbearing of one hundred pounds for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119247:4"/>a year, and ſo rateably, or above twelve pence for making or renewing of the Bond or Bill for the Loane, or for forbearing thereof, or for any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbond or Bill concerning the ſame, ſhalll Forfeit for every ſuch Offence twenty pounds, and have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment for half a year: The one moyety of all which Forfeitures to be to the King our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord, His Heirs and Succeſſors; And the other moiety to the perſons that ſhall ſue for the ſame, in the ſame County where the ſeveral Offences are committed, and not elſewhere.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
